<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The charge of Richard, Lord Bishop of Bath and Wells, to the clergy of his diocese at his primary visitation begun at Axebridge, June 2, 1692</title>
            <author>Kidder, Richard, 1633-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K396</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6408</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12905392</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12905392</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95312</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47322)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95312)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 386:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The charge of Richard, Lord Bishop of Bath and Wells, to the clergy of his diocese at his primary visitation begun at Axebridge, June 2, 1692</title>
                  <author>Kidder, Richard, 1633-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for Brab. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95312:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95312:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARGE OF RICHARD, LORD BISHOP of Bath and Wells, TO THE CLERGY of his DIOCESE, AT HIS <hi>Primary <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation</hi> Begun at AXEBRIDGE, <hi>June</hi> 2. 1692.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Brab. Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:95312:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95312:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Dear Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE deſign of my calling you together at this time is, that I may, as much as lies in me, ſet thoſe things right that are amiſs; and if you meet me here with the ſame purpoſe I cannot but promiſe my ſelf very good ſucceſs from the bleſſing of God and our united Endeavours.</p>
            <p>It ſtands us very much in hand to improve the time we have for the good of thoſe Souls that Chriſt hath purchaſed with his pretious blood. There are many conſiderations which may awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken us to the greateſt diligence in this matter. The care of Souls is of all things of the greateſt weight; We muſt ſhortly give a ſevere account of our diſcharge of this great duty; we have ſins enough of our own to account for, we had not need the addition of the guilt of others; Thoſe that miſcarry through our negligence we muſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for; On the other hand if we uſe due care, and win Souls to God, if we convert Sinners from the evil of their wayes how bleſſed a work will this be, and how great ſhall be our reward? To
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95312:3"/>be thus imployed is a God-like work; 'Tis an imitation of God and our Bleſſed Saviour; 'Tis a work of the greateſt charity, an inſtance of the higheſt wiſdom, an imitation of the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous example of our Lord and Maſter. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, 'tis a work we ſtand obliged to, not onely as we are Chriſtians, but more eſpecially as we are the Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt. we are <hi>ſtewards</hi> of the myſteries of God, <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we are appointed to <hi>govern</hi> and <hi>overſee</hi> the <hi>flock</hi> of <hi>Chriſt, labourers</hi> in God's <hi>Vineyard;</hi> all which expreſſions intimate to us the need of great cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection and diligence. Happy, moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py will thoſe men be who do their utmoſt to gain Souls to God and to righteouſneſs. <hi>He that converteth a ſinner from the Error of his wayes ſhall ſave a Soul from death, and ſhall hide a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Sins,</hi> Jam. 5.20. <hi>And they that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the firmament, and they that turn many to righteouſneſs as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi> Dan. 12.3.</p>
            <p>If we will take the pains to reflect upon the promiſes we made when we entered into Holy Orders, and the Holy Sacrament that then we took upon thoſe promiſes, and whereby we bound ourſelves to make them good, we ſhall find this of mighty force to awaken us to the utmoſt care
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95312:3"/>and circumſpection. We profeſſed then to be <hi>inwardly moved by the Holy Ghoſt and truly called to that holy Office: That we would</hi> diligently <hi>frame and faſhion our own and families lives to the doctrine of Chriſt: Diligently to miniſter the Doctrine and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and Diſcipline of the Church:</hi> That <hi>we would baniſh all erroneous doctrines, and uſe publick and private monitions, and exhortations to the ſick and the whole.</hi> That we would be <hi>diligent</hi> in <hi>prayers and reading and ſtudying the Scripture:</hi> That we would <hi>ſet forward quietneſs, peace and love.</hi> Upon theſe terms we were admitted into this Holy Office.</p>
            <p>How far we have made theſe promiſes good we ought to conſider. God will not be mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If we have failed 'twill concern us highly to return to our duty, and to take that diligent care of our flocks that we may both ſave our <hi>ſelves</hi> and them that <hi>hear</hi> us.</p>
            <p>And to this great end and purpoſe I commend to your care the following particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, That ye would be <hi>Examples</hi> to your people.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.16.</note> Teach them not onely by your <hi>Sermons</hi> but by your <hi>Lives.</hi> So <hi>live</hi> that they may ſafely <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low</hi> you. Tread out the ſteps before them that they are to take towards Heaven. Let them ſee that you do that your ſelves which you perſwade them to do. This is the moſt compendious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95312:4"/>and powerfull way of teaching and perſwaſion.</item>
               <item>2 This is the way that our great Lord and Maſter took. St. <hi>Luke</hi> calls his Goſpel a <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe</hi> of all the things that <hi>Jeſus</hi> began to <hi>Do</hi> and <hi>Teach. Act.</hi> 1.1. He did not onely inſtruct his followers by his Sermons, his Parables, his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, and wiſe Speeches, but by his actions and the whole courſe of his life. They might from his <hi>life</hi> learn that <hi>Piety,</hi> that <hi>Charity,</hi> that <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> that <hi>Abſtraction</hi> from, and <hi>Contempt</hi> of the world which he commended to them from his <hi>Doctrine.</hi> He not onely <hi>commanded</hi> but <hi>led</hi> them as became the great <hi>Captain</hi> of their Salvation. His Example was inſtructive as well as his Sermons. They might ſee in him that exemplifyed which he preached to them. He ſcattered beams of light as he went along, and his diſciples might clearly ſee what they were to do by what he did. He taught them to <hi>believe</hi> in God in all difficulties and <hi>ſtraits,</hi> to <hi>love</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> him, to <hi>worſhip</hi> him and be <hi>reſigned</hi> to his <hi>will:</hi> But then all this might be learned from his <hi>Example</hi> alſo. He truſted in him in the barren <hi>wilderneſs,</hi> and upon the <hi>troubled Sea,</hi> and hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the <hi>Croſs.</hi> He loved him above all, and ſought not his own <hi>glory</hi> but that of him that ſent him. He was much in <hi>Prayer</hi> to God, frequently
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95312:4"/>at the <hi>Temple</hi> where he was <hi>worſhipped,</hi> the zeal of his fathers houſe eat him up; to him he reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf under the greateſt agony, ſaying, <hi>not my will but thine be done. Jeſus</hi> taught his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers exact righteouſneſs, and he practifed it alſo. He taught them to <hi>love</hi> each other and to <hi>forgive</hi> their Enemies. And he gave them a great example of it. For he went about doing good, he fed the hungry, and taught the ignorant, and relieved the oppreſſed, and made joy and gladneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he came: And for his bitter Enemies he with his laſt breath prays for them, <hi>Father forgive them for they know not what they doe.</hi> 'Twere eaſie to ſhew in a great number of inſtances, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> did practiſe himſelf what he taught us. He commends to us humility, and bids us learn of him for he was lowly in heart: nor was there ever ſuch a mirror of profound Humility in the World. The ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Patience,</hi> and <hi>Contempt</hi> of the <hi>World, Fortitude</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> &amp;c. Our Lord taught theſe leſſons by his great Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And thus muſt we do: We muſt <hi>do</hi> as well as <hi>teach.</hi> This is the way to bring Souls to God. Let's hear St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeak. <hi>The Elders which are among you I exhort— Feed the flock of God which is among you, taking the overſight thereof, not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95312:5"/>by conſtraint but willingly, not for filthy lucre's ſake but of a ready mind, neither as being Lords over God's heritage but being Enſamples to the flock.</hi> 1 Pet 5. 1, 2, 3. This way of example it ſeems is the ſitteſt method and courſe; and ſo indeed it is. 'Twill do more good than violence and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion; more than ſubtilty and dry reaſoning. <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men that they may ſee your Good works and glorifie your father which is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Matt. 5.16. Again, <hi>In all things ſhewing thy ſelf a pattern of Good works,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and that he that is of the contrary part may be aſhamed.</hi> Tit. 11.7, 8. This St. <hi>Peter</hi> puts Chriſtians upon as the beſt way to gain upon the Heathen world: <hi>That they may</hi> (ſays he) <hi>by your</hi> Good works, <hi>which they ſhall behold glorify God in the day of viſitation.</hi> 1 Pet. 11.12.</p>
            <p>By this means we ſhall demonſtrate that our Religion is <hi>practicable:</hi> This is of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, for men are too apt to think Religion a yoke too heavy for them to bear: Hence it is that they are diſcouraged. They attempt not to take up a burden which they think they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear. Practice your Religion and you will confute this dangerous miſtake, and they will <hi>follow</hi> that will not <hi>lead</hi> the way. <hi>Jeſus</hi> did thus, as ye have heard. He practiſed his own rules,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95312:5"/>and clothed with our fleſh and natural infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, overcame the Devil and World and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Crown. By his <hi>Precepts</hi> he taught what <hi>we ought</hi> to <hi>do,</hi> and by his <hi>Life</hi> what <hi>might</hi> be done. <hi>Si praecipientem ſequi non potes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lactant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. l. 4, c. 24.</note> 
               <hi>ſequere antecedentem.</hi> Men are apt to follow example, and can never pretend that impoſſible to be done which they ſee done before them.</p>
            <p>Again; An examplary life will much tend to beget in men a belief of the <hi>truth</hi> of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Every man cannot judge of the force of arguments and other motives of Credibility. He that lives well is a good defender of his faith, and will, if not <hi>Convert,</hi> yet, at leaſt <hi>put</hi> to <hi>ſilence</hi> gain-ſayers. The people will think ſin a great <hi>evil</hi> and <hi>heaven</hi> a great <hi>relity</hi> when they ſee their teachers eſchew all appearance of evil and vigorouſly purſue heavenly things. Chriſtian Religion was propagated at firſt by <hi>miracles</hi> and an <hi>holy life: miracles</hi> are <hi>ceaſed</hi> with the reaſon of them; an holy life hath a mighty force ſtill. And did we live up to our Religion we ſhould go far in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing of unbelievers. An example of vertue hath a powerfull influence.</p>
            <p>Beſides what hath been ſaid, an exemplary life would give the people an excellent <hi>idea</hi> of the <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miableneſs</hi> and <hi>glories</hi> of Religion. Certain it is that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95312:6"/>Religion is the moſt excellent thing in the world. Did we diſcern its beauties, and diſcover its perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we could not but be raviſht with it. 'Tis the higheſt perfection of our nature, the greateſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of peace and happineſs; our trueſt intereſt, and our glory, the greateſt advancement that our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are capable of towards God, and eternal reſt. Suppoſe a man to live up to his Religion and how goodly a creature will he be? He will diſcover the beauties of Godlineſs who leads a godly life; He that loves God above all, that fears him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, prays earneſtly to him, gives him continual thanks, and owns him in all his wayes: Such a man will commend <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> which does as he would be done by, who is mercifull to the poor and juſt to all: The modeſt and temperate and humble man commends Sobriety to others moſt powerfully.</p>
            <p>But on the other hand, how great are the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs of a <hi>bad example,</hi> eſpecially in miniſters, and the guides of Souls? who will practiſe that Religion which they ſee diſobeyed by the miniſters thereof? The people will queſtion the truth of that Religion which you <hi>commend</hi> indeed in your Pulpits but <hi>deny</hi> in your Lives: They will queſtion a future ſtate if they ſee you neglect it. They will not be forward to mind heavenly things
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95312:6"/>when they ſee you mind earthly. They'll ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther follow your practice than your Sermons. And will entertain but a mean opinion of that Religion which you preach up and deſpiſe at the ſame time. If you live amiſs you may preach long enough and do no good: Your bad exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will do more hurt than ever your preaching will do good.</p>
            <p>There is no man ſo vile as a profane Miniſter of Religion; He is of all the moſt abject, the moſt ſelf-condemned, and deſtitute of plea, and liable to the heavyeſt plagues of another life. If the Religion he teacheth be <hi>falſe</hi> why does he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to his people? if <hi>good</hi> why does he not practice it? He muſt anſwer for the ſouls he miſleads; Their guilt will be required of him. Oh the miſcheif of ſuch an example! it wounds many Souls at once. It reproaches our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, undermines our Church, breeds Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, produceth open Enemies to our order, our function and conſtitution. Theſe men are the Enemies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> theſe are its aſſaſſinates, from theſe men ſhe hath received the moſt dangerous wounds and blemiſhes. Good God awaken us to a conſideration of our danger this way! That Church can never be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure whoſe pillars and ſupporters are weak and rotten.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:95312:7"/>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt take care that our <hi>families</hi> be exemplary alſo. We muſt ſee that all under our roof be <hi>patterns</hi> of virtue and goodneſs, and that the people may learn to govern their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſervants from what they ſee us do. Hence 'tis required of a Biſhop (who is highly concerned to reprove the faults of thoſe under his charge and influence) not onely that he himſelf ſhould be <hi>blameleſs and of good behaviour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.6, 9. 1 Tim. 3.4, 8, 11.</note> 
               <hi>apt to teach,</hi> &amp;c. but alſo that he ſhould have a well ordered family and <hi>obedient Children,</hi> and then it is added <hi>that he may be able to exhort, and convince gainſayers;</hi> which he will not ſo ſucceſsfully do who hath the ſame diſorders within his own walls, which he ought not to allow in the Church of God. And the ſame reaſon requires that the <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> ſhould not onely themſelves be <hi>grave,</hi> but that their Wives ſhould be <hi>grave, ſober, not ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers,</hi> but <hi>faithfull in all things.</hi> It ſtands you in hand to inſtruct your children and ſervants in the principles of Religion, and the great difference between right and wrong, <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil.</hi> Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs them with the fear of the great God, with ſound principles of true Religion and Vertue. You muſt read the Scriptures couſtantly to them, pray conſtantly with them and for them: make your houſes nurſeries of Piety: Teach your do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95312:7"/>to pray to God, and to give him thanks: uſe ſuch care that it may be difficult for any in your families to miſcarry; ſo order things that your houſes may be ſuch ſchools of vertue that your people may diſcern in your children and ſervants the effects of your care and diſcipline. Baniſh from your own houſes all intemperance and profaneneſs, all evil ſpeaking, and ſuch as are addicted to fraud and deceit. Take up the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt's reſolution. <hi>Him that hath an high look and proud heart will not I ſuffer. Mine Eyes ſhall be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the faithfull of the land, that they may dwell with me: He that walketh in a perfect may be ſhall ſerve me: He that worketh deceit ſhall not dwell in my houſe: He that telleth lies ſhall not tarry in my ſight.</hi> Pſalm 101.5, 6, 7. Endeavour to make your children and ſervants the ſervants of God, and you will ſecure that duty and obedience which is owing to your ſelves and much advance the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of Religion. This is the duty of all, but eſpecially of you that are teachers of others. And this was the care of thoſe who were the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God of old, and will with God's bleſſing be attended with great ſucceſs. <hi>Abraham</hi> was a great example of this care, and found the good effects of it in his life-time. <hi>I know him</hi> (ſays the Lord) <hi>that he will command his Children and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95312:8"/>his houſhold after him, and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord, to do juſtice and judgment.</hi> Gen. 18.19. We read of him that he removed with <hi>Lot,</hi> and the <hi>Souls</hi> which they had <hi>gotten</hi> in <hi>Haran.</hi> ch. 12.5. And elſewhere 'tis ſaid that he armed his <hi>trained,</hi> or <hi>inſtructed</hi> Servants, <hi>born in his own houſe.</hi> ch. 14.14. There is an opinion among the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Jews that theſe Souls were ſuch as he had proſelyted to the true Religion, brought over from Paganiſm to the worſhip of the true and living God.</p>
            <p>And we find great effects of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s care, both in the ſubmiſſion of his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> ch. 22.6, 9. and the admirable fidelity of his Servant. ch. 24.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The next care muſt be in teaching and inſtructing your people. And this you are greatly concerned in. I know there are ſeveral ways of teaching, and therefore I ſhall conſider them apart and ſpeak of them diſtinctly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>preaching</hi> the word of God, or publick expounding the holy Scriptures to our people. This is an unqueſtionable duty and incumbent upon every one that hath undertaken the cure of Souls. St. <hi>Paul</hi> lays a vehement charge upon <hi>Timothy</hi> to diſcharge it. <hi>I charge</hi> thee <hi>before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall judge the quick
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95312:8"/>and the dead at his appearing and his Kingdom. Preach the word, be inſtant in Seaſon, out of Seaſon, reprove, rebuke, exhort with all long-ſuffering and doctrine.</hi> 2 Tim. 4.1, 2. Let's not deceive our ſelves: We are ſtrictly obliged to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of this duty. No condition of life, no circumſtance can excuſe us; where we are are able to do it we muſt do it by our ſelves, and not ſhift off this labour upon others and neglect it our ſelves. We think Mothers obliged (where they are able) to nurſe their own children, and ſhall we neglect our flocks and put them out to be nurſed by Curates, and thoſe too, very often, unfit for that care? Our Saviour and his holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles gave us another ſort of Example. Shall we leave our Sheep, and hunting after fleeces elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where neglect them of whom we have taken the charge? God forbid. <hi>Jeſus</hi> required ſomething more when he put his diſciples on feeding his ſheep. God will not be mocked: He requires a greater care and will bring us to a ſevere ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
            <p>But for the better diſcharge of this duty I muſt commend to you the following particulars.
<list>
                  <item>[1.] That you inſiſt chiefly on the <hi>unqueſtionable</hi> and main things of Religion; avoiding fooliſh queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (Tit. 3.3.) nice ſpeculations and amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95312:9"/>ſing ſubtilties that have no tendency to make men better. acquaint your people with the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and corrupt condition of lapſed mankind, of its weakneſs and inability and obnoxiouſneſs to God's diſpleaſure. Acquaint them with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod God uſed for our redemption by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> which the ſeveral offices of Chriſt and how he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged them; with the nature of the new cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant or covenant of Grace; with the conditions of it on our part; with the nature of a ſaving faith, and the motives of credibility with which the Goſpel is attended. Explain to them the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and neceſſity of repentance, and the danger of delaying it; the great neceſſity of an holy life, of piety, juſtice, charity, temperance, humility, purity and mortification of our luſts and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrong paſſions. Preach frequently againſt the reigning ſins of the time, againſt drunkenneſs, common ſwearing, uncleanneſs, profanation of the Lord's day, neglect of the publick worſhip of God, of publick prayers and ſacraments. Put them upon worſhiping God in their families, upon praying with their children and ſervants. If it be poſſible bring every family to it; preſs upon them the abſolute neceſſity of it, aſſiſt and direct them that they may do it as they ought. Furniſh them with books and helps, and where
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95312:9"/>you cannot afford to be at that expence get the help of thoſe that are able and willing. Let them know the worth of their Souls; the certainty of a future judgment, the vanity of this world and uncertainty of life.</item>
                  <item>[2.] Secure a <hi>good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</hi> Do what you do for God's ſake, and for the good of Souls. Be ſincere and without guile. Do nothing for oſtentation of your wit or learning, nothing for low or mean regards. St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath put what I mean into a few words. <hi>Our Exhortation was not of deceit, nor of uncleanneſs, nor in guile: But as we were allowed of God to be put in truſt with the Goſpel, even ſo we ſpeak, not as pleaſing men but God, who tryeth our hearts: For neither at any time uſed we flattering words, as ye know; nor a cloke of covetouſneſs, God is witneſs. Nor of men ſought we glory, neither of you, nor yet of others, when we might have been burthenſome as the Apoſtles of Chriſt.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 2.3, 4, 5, 6. Be conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to your ſelf of no other deſign but the good of Souls and facilitating your future account, and you will not miſs your reward hereafter whatever be your ſucceſs here.</item>
                  <item>[3.] You muſt uſe great diligence alſo. <hi>Preach the word; be inſtant in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, out of ſeaſon.</hi> 2. Tim. 4.2. <hi>Till I come, give at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine. — Meditate upon theſe things, give thy ſelf wholly to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95312:10"/>them, that thy profiting may appear to all.</hi> 1 Tim. 4.13, 15. If after all you take care that your preaching</item>
                  <item>[4.] be attended with an <hi>unblamable</hi> life you will render it more effectual. <hi>Theſe things command and teach: Let no man deſpiſe thy youth: But be thou an example of the believers, in word, in converſation, in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, in purity.</hi> 1 Tim. 4.11, 12. This was the courſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> took himſelf. 1 Theſſ. 2.10. And you muſt eſpecially take care to carry your ſelves with all gentleneſs, and charity towards your people. Let them ſee that you have for them the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions of a Father, and that you can bear with their frowardneſs and infirmities. Let them ſee that you love their Souls, and ſeek them and not theirs. If they be unkind be gentle towards them and overcome evil with good. Let's hear how St. <hi>Paul</hi> did. He was <hi>gentle</hi> as a <hi>nurſe</hi> to her children, content to <hi>dye</hi> for them, he had the tenderneſs of a <hi>Father.</hi> 1 Theſſ. 2.7, 8, 11. <hi>The ſervant of God muſt not ſtrive but be gentle unto all men, apt to teach, patient. In meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth.</hi> 2 Tim. 2.24, 25.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95312:10"/>
            <p n="2">II. Another way of teaching is by way of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſing;</hi> this, I fear, is too much neglected. And yet nothing can be more neceſſary or of greater moment.<note place="margin">Can. LIX.</note> Our Church does by a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non ſtrictly oblige you to ſpend half an hour e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sunday and Holyday in this exerciſe, and upon any neglect thereof directs that the Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be reproved ſharply, and after this upon neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect to be ſuſpended, and then if he do it not to be excommunicated. You are alſo obliged by a law as you may ſee in the <hi>Rubrick</hi> at the end of the Catechiſm in the Common Prayer: But you are obliged to it as it is a main part of your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial duty. And I muſt put you upon the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent diſcharge of it, and do require you to do it by vertue of your canonical obedience. This is the way to build wiſely, and without it you build without a foundation. Your Sermons will be of little fruit if you take not this courſe, and if you do they are like to be of great. Do this as you ought and you will ſoon find it (I can ſay, I thank God I have found if ſo) very advantageous. But then you muſt explain the Catechiſm to them, and take ſuch pains in it that they (who are thus taught) may not onely be able to ſay it without Book, but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what they ſay, and expreſs themſelves
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95312:11"/>in other words, by which you may be aſſured that they do underſtand it aright.</p>
            <p n="3">III. There is another way of teaching which I may call <hi>occaſional</hi> that is not to be neglected. When you viſit your people, or they viſit you, take all occaſions you can to inſtill into them principles of Religion and Vertue. Our Saviour taught frequently this way, and 'twill well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come you to follow his example. And you will do well not onely to take but ſeek all occaſions of doing your people good.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, You muſt alſo be much in <hi>Prayer</hi> that God would proſper the good Seed which you ſow. <hi>Paul</hi> may plant and <hi>Apollos</hi> water, but it is <hi>God</hi> which gives the increaſe. And here I commend to you all prayer, private in your Cloſets, and prayer in your Families, and the publick pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in your Churches. And for the laſt of theſe I would have you very carefull to omit no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of reading them fully as they are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and with great devotion and reverence. Do all you can to bring your people to them, and to keep up the credit and reputation of this publick ſervice of the Church. Labour much with your people to take off their prejudices, and to bring them to a better ſenſe of things. And have a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95312:11"/>care to read thoſe occaſional prayers on the Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing days, and other times appointed, in behalf of the King and Queen and theſe Kingdoms: We have great cauſe to keep theſe Faſts religiouſly, and to ſolicit the protection of Heaven: Our all lies at ſtake, and our help is onely in the name of the Lord, who made Heaven and Earth.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, You are alſo to <hi>adminiſter</hi> the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> as is appointed by the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is the Sacrament of Initiation: By this we are entred into the Church: You are to take care (as directed in the Rubrick) that this be not delayed, and that it be done in the Church in the face of the Congregation. You are alſo to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain in your Sermons the nature of this Sacrament, and the grounds of Infant Baptiſm, and often to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain the Baptiſmal Vow, and call on your People to reflect upon it, and to conſider the obligation that ariſeth thence to a life of Vertue and Religion.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly neglected by the People to the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of Chriſtian Piety. You are to take great pains in this matter. Let you people know that they are not at Liberty to receive it or omit it. That it is not onely commanded but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by our dying Maſter, and dying for us, and as a ſtanding memorial of his death, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95312:12"/>unparallelled love to us. If they plead the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of receiving amiſs, lay before them the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger alſo of not receiving at all. If they ſay they are not fit ask them when they will, and whether or not they be fit to die? and die they muſt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be fit or not. Take off all their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. Shew them how much frequent commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion would advance Piety and good Will. Make them ſenſible of the great danger of neglecting this duty, and the great ingratitude to their dying Lord. But miſtake me not. I am not after all for admitting promiſcuouſly all that may offer themſelves. The young muſt firſt be well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, the ſcandalous muſt be warned, and kept back, as the Rubrick directs, and thoſe that have lived in variance and enmity muſt be reconciled. Frequent communion and due care and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline would greatly amend this lower World.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, You are diligently to viſit the ſick. The people indeed are obliged to ſend for you, but if they do not 'twill well become you to go to them. This viſitation of the ſick muſt by no meanes be neglected, tho' as the caſe may be we have ſometimes but a faint proſpect of doing any good. There are many caſes that will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the greateſt prudence and patience alſo. Perhaps you go to a man that hath lived a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95312:12"/>and profane life. You muſt have a care you do not ſend him to another world with falſe hopes; have a care you do not ſpeak peace where God ſpeaks none; awaken him to a ſence of his <hi>Sin</hi> as well as <hi>Danger.</hi> Shew him the <hi>evil</hi> of <hi>irreligion</hi> and <hi>profaneneſs;</hi> ſhew him the great <hi>ingratitude</hi> of it with reſpect to the great God, the authour of our breath and being; Inquire ſtrictly of him as to his paſt life; Whether he have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured any, or be in enmity: Put him upon <hi>reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> and <hi>reconciliation</hi> forthwith. Put him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on owning his wickedneſs to his ſhame, let him ſend for the companions of his folly, and warn them to amend their lives, and to break off the evil Courſe they are in. Let him be put upon all acts of charity and mercy according to his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, upon patience under his ſickneſs, as that which is but a juſt puniſhment of his Sins. Let him be made ſenſible of the danger of a late <hi>repentance,</hi> as we call that ſorrow which in our ſickneſs we expreſs on account of our Sins. Whether it be after a Godly ſort, and unto life God knows, we cannot tell. We have cauſe to fear that ſuch mens ſorrow is like that of a malefactors, not for his <hi>fault</hi> but for his being <hi>apprehended:</hi> The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is perhaps ſorry, not that he hath been <hi>wicked</hi> but that God is <hi>juſt.</hi> Let us not neglect ſuch a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95312:13"/>ſinner, if he die we muſt leave him to God: If he recover we had need follow him, and put him upon paying his vows. We have ſeen ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny return to their vomit, and have proved their former ſorrow not to have been after a Godly ſort. You will find ſome others <hi>fearful</hi> beyond <hi>cauſe,</hi> and <hi>trembling</hi> leſt they ſhould fall ſhort of God's Kingdom. Some caſes you will meet with of conſiderable difficulty. In all which you are to uſe the greateſt ſimplicity and diligence and courage too that you may miniſter where you can to the neceſſities of the ſick: And to that purpoſe you are to pray for them with great fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, and for your ſelves alſo you muſt pray that God would give you wiſdom and courage to diſcharge your duty as ye ought.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, You are with all your might to ſet forward <hi>quietneſs, peace,</hi> and <hi>love,</hi> as ye promiſed before ye were ordained. And this muſt be part of your ſtudy: Prevent as much as you can miſunderſtaning among your people, quarrels and ſuits of Law. Make peace among thoſe that are at variance, and live at peace as much as ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in you. Do what you can to perſuade to love and to good works. And tho' there be among your people men of different opinions, yet let them all know that that will not excuſe their
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95312:13"/>love to each other. This is of the life and eſſence of Religion, it can never be without it. Preſs this hard upon your people and let them all ſee you practice it. Be kind to all, do them good offices, be ſo to them who do not attend your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry as they ſhould; overcome them with kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs if it be poſſible, and let them ſee you do not want compaſſion for them whatever their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes or prejudices may be. Widen not differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces but do what is poſſible to heal them, and to preſerve the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I commend to you great care of the poor and afflicted among your people. Let the poor find you their Patrons. Relieve them as far as you can, and ſtir up others to do it. Viſit them in their Sickneſs as readily as ye do the rich; get them inſtructed, and eſpecially be kind to God's poor, <hi>i. e.</hi> to thoſe who are diligent in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and are willing to be inſtructed. And be greatly carefull of the oppreſſed and afflicted of thoſe that mourn for the death of friends, of thoſe who meet with great loſſes; comfort them and let them ſee that you mourn with them. Take this occaſion to awaken them to a greater care to ſerve God, that they may not be miſerable in both worlds. If you watch theſe ſeaſons
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95312:14"/>and lay hold of them you may do very much good.</p>
            <p>In a word, if you will take this courſe, and purſue it vigourouſly, and conſtanly implore the Divine aid and aſſiſtance, I make no doubt at all but you may do much, and that you will both ſave your ſelves and them that hear you.</p>
            <p>There are beſides what I put you in mind of, ſome other things which I think my ſelf obliged to lay before you. And tho' the things I have named already do more immediately concern your office and function, yet the things I have ſtill to offer will be worthy of your regard and care. I have told you what you are to <hi>do</hi> for the more ſuccesfull diſcharge of your Holy Office: I will now put you in mind of ſome things you are to <hi>be aware of:</hi> And</p>
            <p>Firſt, Have a care that you give not <hi>Certificates</hi> and <hi>Teſtimonials</hi> to thoſe who come for Orders or Inſtitution unleſs you well know the perſons whom you commend. It ſtands me in hand not to <hi>lay hands ſuddenly</hi> on any man, and you ought to be <hi>carefull</hi> how you give your hands al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. When you commend them, you commend them to the ſervice of God and the moſt holy func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I ſhould be very tender of commending a Servant (eſpecially in a ſervice of truſt) to my
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95312:14"/>friend or equall leſt he ſhould deceive him by proving unfaithfull: Does it not become us then to take great care whom we commend to this ſervice of God, and to be ſtewards of his myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries? The <hi>Canon</hi> requires the knowledge of the perſon commended, three years before:<note place="margin">Can. XXXIV.</note> I would have you keep to that rule; And take ſuch care that I may have no cauſe to ſuſpect your teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monials.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Have a care of the <hi>Titles</hi> you grant to thoſe who come for Orders. We cannot or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain without a title, nor is it fit we ſhould.<note place="margin">Can. XXXIII.</note> If we do we are juſtly liable to maintain the Clerk, and if we refuſe that, to be ſuſpended. This is a moſt wholeſome Law, and for the publick good: But ſome men have granted <hi>falſe Titles</hi> and ſupplanted a moſt excellent Conſtitution. The <hi>Canon</hi> requires a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>undoubted Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> of this Title: But many have given ſuch as are undoubtedly falſe. And by this means the Church hath been filled with ſupernumerary and very poor Miniſters, who for want of bread have been tempted to do mean and vile things to keep themſelves from ſtarving. And theſe men muſt be unlearned of courſe being deſtitute of all means that tend to their obtaining it. If you give them falſe titles you ſet them wrong
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95312:15"/>at firſt. When they are to be ordained they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that they are inwardly moved to that holy Office <hi>by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and <hi>truly called</hi>— and <hi>that, according to the order of this Church.</hi> And yet he that ſays this brings <hi>a lye in his right hand.</hi> I will tell you what I expect from you for the future. I will accept no Title from any of you unleſs you do, under your hands and ſeals, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that you will allow the perſon to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained ſuch a Sum <hi>per annum</hi> for <hi>Supplying</hi> ſuch a place, and that you will not diſmiſs him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of your <hi>Dioceſan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Have a great care that you do not preſent thoſe young perſons to be confirmed by the Biſhop, who cannot render an <hi>account of their Faith</hi> as the <hi>Canon</hi> directs.<note place="margin">Canon LXI. Rubr. after the Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm.</note> The <hi>Rubrick</hi> requires that the perſon to be confirmed ſhould be of <hi>a competent age,</hi> that he ſhould have a God-father or God-mother a preſent witneſs of the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and that the fitneſs of the perſon to be confirmed be atteſted by the Miniſter with the ſaid perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lives. I am moſt ready to confirm young perſons provided this preparation and proviſion be made. Otherwiſe, I ſhall appoint ſome time for the ſolemn performance of this ancient and holy Action: And I ſhall endeavour ſo to do it that it may gain its end, and ſerve to ſet us
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95312:15"/>forward towards the Kingdom of Heaven. The practice of Confirmation is both ancient and of admirable uſe, and may be ſo managed (if it be not huddled over) that it may be an excellent inſtrument of Religion. What the intention of Confirmation is may be learned from the office our Church hath appointed for it. We then take upon our ſelves that vow of Baptiſm, which, when we were young, we made by our ſureties; we own that Religion our ſelves which, when we were young, others profeſſed on our behalf. This is the reaſon of the inſtitution. And therefore you that are to prepare perſons for Confirmation may hence underſtand what you are to aime at: You are to put them in <hi>mind</hi> of their <hi>baptiſmal Vow,</hi> to <hi>explain</hi> the <hi>ſeveral parts</hi> of it, to <hi>inſtruct</hi> them in the principles of that Religion which they profeſs, to put them upon owning it publickly, and not to be aſhamed of the Goſpell and Croſs of Chriſt. This is an admirable inſtitution and wonderfully fitted for the advancement of true Religion. There was ſomething like this practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the Jewiſh Church. He that was circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in his Infancy, when he became of the age of 13 years, took upon himſelf the Moſaical pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and then he was called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>ſon of the precept;</hi> If after this he broke the Law he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95312:16"/>was anſwerable for that breach, and not his Parents or Sureties. We are in our office of Baptiſm to mind the <hi>Sponſors</hi> for the baptized infant to take care that the child be inſtructed; And that the children be minded of their baptiſmal vow, and taught <hi>all</hi> the <hi>things which a Chriſtian ought to know and believe to his Souls health.</hi> And after this they are warned to bring them to the Biſhop to be confirmed. Your care then I muſt deſire, and if that be not wanting you ſhall find me moſt ready to do what belongs to me.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Beware of <hi>non-reſidence.</hi> You are obliged to reſide by the Law. Upon <hi>Vicaridges</hi> you are bound to reſide by Vertue of the <hi>Oath</hi> you have taken. That Oath obligeth you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you are diſpenſed with by the Biſhop: That indeed is the onely way to ſecure the non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Vicar from Perjury. Nothing elſe but that can do it. 'Tis nothing to this purpoſe what was the reaſon why all Vicars are obliged to take this Oath. When they have taken it they are obliged; if they reſide not (unleſs diſpenſed with) they are <hi>foreſworn.</hi> 'Tis certainly ſo, whatever a late Author in his book of Pluralities hath advanced to the contrary. An Oath is not to be trifled with. For my part I cannot ſee how <hi>non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> can be juſtifyed, therefore I muſt and do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95312:16"/>you to reſide upon your Cures. I hope I need ſay no more of the reſidence of <hi>Vicars,</hi> they are obliged by Oath, and very obnoxious if they reſide not. But there are other <hi>non-reſidents</hi> that give great ſcandall. Some have two Livings and reſide on neither as they ought. Others that have but one reſide not on that. They take a Curacy, or purſue a Lecture elſewhere; They chooſe to live in a better aire, or among more faſhionable perſons than their poor neighbors are. They are for the converſation of Gentlemen and Men of learning; others ſpend their time vainly and fooliſhly and neglect thoſe poor Souls which they have taken the charge of. Did <hi>Jeſus</hi> do thus, did the Apoſtles, did the ancient Holy Biſhops and Martyrs thus leave their Sheep? Did <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſpend his time among Grandees and the Wits of the age? He preached much in <hi>Galilee</hi> an obſcure and mean Country. He converſed with poor and weak, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and illiterate people. Good God awaken us to a juſt ſence of things, and grant that while we leave our flocks the Souls that in our abſence paſs into another world do not carry thither juſt complaints againſt us. We ſhall have the blood of thoſe Souls to anſwer for whom we have neglected.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Neglect not thoſe days of Faſting ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Authority, nor any of thoſe <hi>Prayers</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:95312:17"/>which are ſent you, and required to be uſed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the preſent ſtate of affairs. I hope you need not to be put in mind of theſe things, becauſe you have taken an Oath to their preſent Majeſties, and are I hope, ſenſible how much lies at ſtake. Our Religion, our Liberties and Properties, our Lives, our All call for this at our hands. We have the ſtrongeſt obligations both from <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</hi> Beſides we ſhall be ſelf con-demned if we are not hearty to that Government to which we have ſworn, and to which we ſtand obliged ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral wayes. We are very vile if we be not true to that Government which we have ſo ſolemnly owned: I am not willing to believe ſo hard a thing of you. If there be any ſuch I wiſh they may not know the difference between a mild and gentle Government (under which we are) and the inſolence of a foreign Tyrant: I wiſh they may never know what arbitrary Power and draggooning mean. Keep the days of Faſting with all manner of care; put your people in mind of them and give them due warning of their approach. And make the people ſenſible how much they are concerned in this matter.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, You are alſo to take great care that you do not marry any without <hi>Banns</hi> or <hi>Licence,</hi> and that in this matter you govern your ſelves
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95312:17"/>by the <hi>Rubrick</hi> and <hi>Canon.</hi> The Miniſter that offends is liable to be ſuſpended for three years.<note place="margin">Canon LXII.</note> And to the ſame penalty is he liable that marries thoſe that are licenſed at unſeaſonable times, or in a private place. Nor may he do it with Banns without the conſent of Parents. And he that offends, tho' in an exempt Church,<note place="margin">Canon LXIII.</note> is liable to the ſame penalty. This is the penalty, and yet as great as it is it hath not proved ſufficient to reſtrain bad men; Inſomuch that other ways have been thought upon by our Law-makers to keep theſe bad men in awe. And there was a Bill on foot in Parliament not long ſince to puniſh it with death. I am ſure the <hi>Fault</hi> is great whatever the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be. To ſteal a woman without conſent of Parents is no ſmall ſin. But as great as that is 'tis not to be compared with that of the Miniſter. He cannot be ſuppoſed under the like temptation, and ought to be of a virtue more conſpicuous. The Miniſter hath no plea, unleſs he plead po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty: But the theif and highwayman may plead this as juſtly as he. This plea ought not to ſave the robber from death, nor this offender from the penalty of our conſtitution.</p>
            <p>That Miniſter that takes the liberty of Clan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtin mariages muſt needs be an abandoned wretch. He does that which is moſt vile and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95312:18"/>his function. He proſtitutes this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly State, and joyns them together whom God hath not joyned, and nature hath ſeparated. He knows not the miſchief he does. For what he knows he marries thoſe that are married, or that ought not to marry: He may bleſs the inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and the moſt unclean mixtures which God abhors, and nature it ſelf forbids. What miſchief to families, what horror to the minds of the married perſons, what confuſion and guilt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows not from thence? There's hardly any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment great enough for ſo great a ſinner. And ſure I am there are leſs offences than this which our Laws have made Capitall. I cannot think ſo hardly of any man that hears me as to ſuppoſe him guilty of ſo great a Crime.</p>
            <p>Marriage is Honourable in all, 'tis an holy ſtate, 'twas appointed in the ſtate of innocence, our Lord gave it credit by his preſence and firſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle: No wonder, for 'tis, tho' not ſtrictly a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, yet, a <hi>myſtery,</hi> a <hi>type</hi> of the union betwixt Chriſt and his Church. So that whether we look to its inſtitution, or to its reference to Chriſt and his Church, 'tis an honourable and holy ſtate, and ought not to be contemned, much leſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted. What hath been ſaid is true of lawfull marriages; But he that joyns thoſe together who
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95312:18"/>ought not to be joyned, he defaces this ſacred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, he profanes this holy Type of heavenly things, he deſtroyes as much as he can the figure of that Union which is betwixt Chriſt and his Church. We ſay all Marriages are made in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: In which common ſaying there may be an higher ſence implyed than is commonly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; but this can onely be meant of lawfull Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages. For others they are contrived by thoſe that belong to another Kingdom. It will ill become a Miniſter of Chriſt to have any hand in ſo deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a practice.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, You are to take great care to keep a Regiſter of Chriſtenings, Weddings, and Burials. This is a matter of great moment, and that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the eſtates and quiet of others is greatly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. You will learn what your duty in this matter is from the <hi>Canon,</hi> and I beſeech you neglect it not.<note place="margin">Can. LXX.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things laſt named require our care, and and our Canons and Conſtitutions direct us in the whole matter. There are ſtill ſome things behind which I muſt alſo lay before you as things tending very much to the good of the whole, and they are theſe that follow.</p>
            <p>I ſhall as far as I am able <hi>Ordain</hi> at the uſual times appointed by our Church. And then as I muſt require the Arch-deacons to attend and offer thoſe who come for Orders, ſo I deſire you as you
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95312:19"/>have occaſion to give out for me that I do expect that thoſe who offer themſelves for holy Orders ſhould come to me ſome time before, that I may have time to inquire carefully into their <hi>lives,</hi> as well as examine them as to their <hi>faith</hi> and knowledge. 'Tis unreaſonable to come for Orders but a day or two before the ordination Sunday. I cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of ſuch a practice as this unleſs I would lay hands ſuddenly, and be a partaker of other mens ſins. 'Tis a matter that requires greater care, and more time. He that is to be ordained ought to ſpend ſome time in preparation for it, and the holy Sacrament attending upon it. Some time in Faſting and holy Exerciſes, and in ſuch a courſe of devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and abſtraction from the world as that holy fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſacred office requires at our hands.</p>
            <p>I muſt alſo deſire you ſo to contrive things that thoſe of you who live near to each other would ſometimes meet together, and when you do ſo be uſefull in your converſation with each other. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult how you may do the moſt good to your peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, exhort one another to love and to good works. Reſolve to be faithfull to each other, and if you ſee any thing amiſs in any of your Brethren reproach them not, but privately and gently tell them what you think may be reproveable. Speak ill of no man, eſpecially where you know no evil; and where you do, let the offender have the firſt notice of his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95312:19"/>fault from you. 'Tis unreaſonable to publiſh a man's faults to another, and not tell him of them that is faulty. Perhaps by this courſe he would deſiſt. Endeavour in your Converſation to be ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary that ye go away better than you came to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. You that are wiſe and more learned may on theſe occaſions afford great help to the younger of the Clergy, and leſs experienced. You may do them much good in directing their ſtudies, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them with the beſt method of diſcharging their Office. Much good may be done this way: You may alſo conſult together to aſſiſt the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows and children of Clergy-men deceaſed, and to make their ſorrows as light as you can.</p>
            <p>Let it not be in the power of any man to ſow diſcord among you. Live in perfect peace with each other. If any difference ariſe end it among your ſelves, or refer the matter to one of your Brethren. What miſchief will your differences produce among your people? They'll be apt enough to go to law when they ſee you do it.</p>
            <p>Be carefull you do not exceed in your Funerall Sermons in the praiſes of the dead. If you do the people will be apt to think themſelves ſafe, if they follow the Example which you commend. Have the greateſt charity for the deceaſed, but at the ſame time have a care of them who do ſurvive. I doubt much miſchief hath been done this way.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:95312:20"/>
            <p>For the Diſſenters among you treat them with humanity, and do all you lawfully can to reduce them. Let them ſee you love their Souls, and that all the pains you take about them proceeds from that principle. You may overcome them perhaps by Gentleneſs and Goodneſs, and if you do 'twill be the nobleſt Victory, and of the greateſt import.</p>
            <p>Abſtain from all appearance of <hi>Evil.</hi> Shun any thing that looks like a fault. Your reputation ought to be tender in your own Eyes as well as in thoſe of others. You ought to be <hi>free</hi> from <hi>ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi> as well as fault, as <hi>Ceſar</hi> ſaid his wife ought to be. Avoid all occaſions of evil, all tendencies, and temptations to it. <hi>Go about, go about O Nazarite, and come not near a Vineyard.</hi> This was a ſaying among the Jews to warn men that they might fly all occaſions of evil. The <hi>Nazarite</hi> that was not allowed to taſt of the liquor of the grape was advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to go through a Vineyard. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things that perhaps are not in themſelves ſtrictly unlawfull, which yet a Divine ought not to allow himſelf in. Where the thing is doubtfull or of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ill fame it well becomes you to forbear. There are ſome games, ſome forms of ſpeech, ſome faſhionable modes of drinking, ſome garbs, ſome practices (allowable in other men) which you will do well to forbear: It becomes us not to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent publick houſes, to be often ſeen in Fairs and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95312:20"/>Markets, or imployed in ſecular matters which yet are not things unlawfull in themſelves. The Prieſts under the Law were not at liberty even where the people were. And that in them was reckoned a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filement which in the people was not a fault. We are ſet apart to an holy Office, and the ancient <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> of the Church laid great reſtraints upon that Order of men.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Let no man deſpiſe you. You'll ſay you cannot help that; honour and fame be it never ſo great a good is in other mens keeping. And yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives this advice both to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> [1 Tim. 4.12. Tit. 2.15.] But then he puts them upon the onely courſe to place themſelvs beyond Contempt. To <hi>Timothy</hi> thus. <hi>But be thou an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the believers, in word, in converſation, in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, in purity. Till I come give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to doctrine: Neglect not the gift that is in thee by prophecy, with laying on the hands of the Preſbytery. Meditate upon theſe things, give thy ſelf wholly to them, that thy profiting may appear to all. Take heed unto thy ſelf and to thy doctrine; continue in them: for in doing this thou ſhalt ſave thy ſelf and them that hear thee.</hi> [1 Tim. 4.12, 13, 14, 15, 16.] To <hi>Titus</hi> he had ſaid, <hi>In all things ſhewing thy ſelf a pattern of good works. In doctrine</hi> ſhewing <hi>uncorrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, gravity, ſincerity; ſound ſpeech that cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95312:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>that he that is of the contrary part, may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med having no evil to ſay of you.</hi> [Tit. 2.7, 8.] This is the way not to be deſpiſed. None that know you will deſpiſe you if you do thus. They may not love you, but they cannot deſpiſe you. Do nothing that is mean, and that will expoſe you to contempt. This is the way not to be deſpiſed. Reverence your ſelves and your holy function, and let men deſpiſe you, that know you, if they can. The truth is, this courſe will raiſe you above contempt. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, he that does low and mean things will be deſpiſed. More ſtill they will be deſpiſed by evil men, by thoſe who ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fond of their company, and partners in their folly. A vicious Gentleman may embrace but cannot but deſpiſe a vicious Clergyman. And he cannot but have a reverence for vertue and real goodneſs who is otherwiſe none of its Votaries.</p>
            <p>To conclude: Reflect upon your Holy Calling and on the Vows that are upon you. Adorn your profeſſion, and be examples to your flock. Vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly purſue your great end, and follow the ſteps of your great Maſter. Be inſtant in your Calling, and diligently watch over your ſelves and people, and you ſhall ſave your ſelves and them that hear you: And when your great Lord and Saviour ſhall appear, ye ſhall likewiſe appear with him in Glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95312:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
